Many people are still unsure how to
get the best narration using Suno.   The
first thing you need to keep
in mind is this: Suno wasn't
created specifically for
voice-over work.  What we're managing to
do are methods that I'm validating
and that are working.  One
super important detail: no matter how much you
force any prompt in Suno to
narrate the way you want, it
will never deliver 100% the way
you described it in the commands.  There in the
prompt, because Suno interprets and
delivers the voice based on your script.  That's what
Suno was created for, to create
emotions based on the lyrics of the music.  But what
are we doing here?  We
are taking scripts and transforming
them so that they can be narrated on Suno.  The
advantage of this is that it allows him to
convey much more emotion.  If you're going to
tell a children's story, it
delivers with a much greater depth of emotion
than Eleven Lives.
Perhaps not much bigger, but with
greater ease.  If you need to
narrate, I don't know, maybe a hymn,
right?  Not praise, but forgiveness.  If you're
making a video about
Bible stories, not praise music, because praise music is
music, right?  So you go there and you want
him to narrate with emotion, with depth.
The Sun can't do that because it will take
the text, interpret what's there, and
deliver that depth to you.  And then there
are techniques where you take
long scripts and manage to transform
that narration so that it becomes
linear.  What is linear narration
in Suno?  Actually, that's not the
correct terminology.  I'm the one who gives it that name, right?
Linear narration.  This refers to when the voice you
chose to narrate the video, and even
the background music, remain
similar, even though they were created in
different generations.  So that's what I was
able to find out here on Suno.  For that very reason
, I've created an e-book that I'll
make available to you here in the
description and in the first
pinned comment, which shows the correct way to
start a conversation in the chat.  There
's also a list with many prompts already there
for you to copy and make
corrections in the prompt where you force
SUN to deliver the best result.
So I'm going to open this up, show you
exactly what I did in one of my
tests, and I'll leave that test and the
prompt used in that test here in the
description so you can copy and
replicate it in your projects.
Suddenly, if you're someone already well-
versed in prompt production and
script organization, what I'm about to
share with you will be a good starting point
for creating and developing your
projects here at Suno.  Okay,
let me show you on the screen
exactly what I did.  First, I
want to introduce you to the initial idea,
where I used prompts generated directly in the
GPT chat.  Then he handed me this one here
.  I'll grab the second one right away.   Once upon a time, there
was
a little snail named Lumo.
Oh,
he carried his house on his back, can you
see?  It's a soft voice,
telling the story of a snail.  There's
some background music, even though you're asking
to force it not to have any.  This is impossible
to remove.  It's possible that in future
updates Suno will actually allow
you to, look, I don't want music in this
part, I only want voice.  Okay, then
he takes it off.  But initially, to be able to
download it after it's already been generated in this version,
you need to be a subscriber to the
Premiere plan.  Then you'll go into the studio
with this music that you've created.  There
you can separate the Steam accounts, everything will be
fine.  I explain this within my
training program.  It's a more complex business now
.  There's no point in me trying to make a
video here on YouTube showing you everything,
like how to create the voice, narrate, remove the background,
separate and edit the video, because then it'll just
be a two-hour video and nobody
will watch it.  Here I need to show you
at least the basics, okay?  So let's go.   So this
is the result that
chatpt gave me.  Then I retrieved the
results from the prompts I had
developed.  So here I have a
flat music option.  Why
flat music?  Because I forced Suno here to
at least try not to give me
any music, or if he does give me any
music, that it's as minimally perceptible as
possible.  Of course it's not possible, okay?  But
look at the difference.  I'm going to put it
here, press play, so we can listen to this one
.   Once upon a time, there was
a little snail named
Lumo, and it began silently.  [music]
Pay attention to the background music,
how it's very soft, very flat,
almost nonexistent.  At certain points you
'll realize that yes, it has music just
like all the others.
But there was something different about him.
Only.  Oh, I'll put it further ahead so you can
understand when the music has a bit
more emphasis.  Are you
lost?  "Oh,"
asked a ladybug landing beside him
. "
Pianzinho there, very quiet. Now I
'm going to show you an option where, in my
own [programs], you can
ask it to insert music
contextualizing the story, okay? Look
, here are two versions. I'll put this one here
for us to see. Once upon a time, there was
a little snail named Lumo.
Did you notice that it starts with piano, something more
childish? That's because in the prompt where I
asked, I already configured it to be
music geared towards a children's channel. And up
here you can see that there's
part one and part two. So this
is part one, where I generated the
same story, okay? I generated it forcing the
voice, everything correctly. Then I took
that same voice, that same track that
it put in, put it back here and
asked it to generate part two. So,
look how interesting. I'll put
part one here, so you understand.
Once upon a time, there was a little snail named
Lumo.
He carried his house on his back.
That little piano, right? No."  This is piano music
, I forgot the name, but it's in the background.
Look how it sounds in the middle. [music]
No,
I just haven't arrived yet.
Okay, right? Now look how
part two of this same script turned out. You can see
I even liked it here, because I'm
going to use it, right? So I'll leave it as a like.
That way I can come here to filters and
only show what I liked, see? Then
only the two will appear here. Oh, one
important thing so you don't get lost like
I was getting lost, I've already created a
workspace called narrations, okay? So
you can find your results
more easily later. I made a mess of
things, I said: "No, stop, stop, let
me organize." I created the workspace here and that's it
. So, I came here, see. Now let's go to
part two. I talked and talked and ended up
disrupting your train of thought, right?
So, just one more little bit of part one.
Lumo replied calmly with [music].
She picked up the piano music. Let's go.
Same.
Time passed,
same piano
And the world seemed to get bigger and bigger.
Same voice and the same sensitivity for
narrating. So you realized that there are
techniques to reach this level? You
can see that this is quite different
from where we have the flat music. Look
. Once upon a time there was a little snail
called Lumo.
Almost zero. It's a very low background music
, maybe you can't even hear
it. Anyway, now let me show you
exactly how I created this
text in the GPT chat. I only asked him the
following: I need a
children's script of up to 5 minutes exclusively
to be used in Suno and we need to
force him to only narrate. So we
have to put a prompt that forces
him to only narrate what I wrote and
very soft background music. Look, here it is.
This is the prompt I used to
start the conversation. If you want to
copy it, no problem. Then here
's his delivery. He gave me the
prompt already saying that I wanted a
female voice in Brazilian Portuguese. Then he
gave me the negative prompt, which is for
us to copy and put there too, since in
S there's no option.  So you can insert the
negatives, right, that you don't want to appear
in the song. And finally, he gave me the
lyrics perfectly. Look here. Spoking
pause. Yeah, want to see? Look, there's even a
dramatic pause, already in two parts, right?
I asked him for up to 5 minutes and
I told him that Suno's limit is
up to 2,500, 3,000 characters. That's not the
limit, the actual limit is up to 5,000
characters. But I ask for this limit of
up to 2,500 to 3,000 characters because all
artificial intelligence, however good
it may be, at some point it
hallucinates or it starts to change its voice, there's no
way to avoid it, okay? So, to
prevent hallucinations, he already
gave it to me in parts here up to about
2,000-something characters. Then he
did part two, look here. Spoking,
okay? Until the end. And then I took this
, put it in Suno, took the  I
also took the negative prompt to Suno,
look, I also took it there and asked them to
generate it. Then there are some settings that I
teach in my training, you know,
how you do the strangeness,
to match the voice that has already been generated.
All of that is in my training,
but the basics so you can already
grasp this, which I'll leave in the
description, and build your script,
your narration, are here. There's no
complexity, it's training, and you
start to notice the differences between
one thing and another that Suno is
delivering, and then you correct them little by little
. So I think this video,
despite being summarized, I'm sure
will give you a huge clarity on how
you can use Suno to make
your narrations. And guys, take advantage of it
because it's very cheap. If I'm not
mistaken, each narration, delivered with
background music and the narration itself, costs
around 5 to 10 cents of reais,
not even dollars, 5 to 10 cents of
reais. So it's very cheap, right?
Much cheaper.  Even cheaper than Levabs, which,
for me at least
for now, is better quality.
So don't forget, okay?
My training is in the description, and there's also this
ebook with all the explanations of these
prompts. I'll leave it at that for now,
and we'll see each other in the next video. A
big hug and goodbye.